

SENIOR ENGINEERING LEADER · COMPUTER SECURITY EXPERT · IT SECURITY ARCHITECT

💌 diego@zzamboni.org · 🏕 zzamboni.org · 🟕 zzamboni · 🖸 zzamboni · 🚨 zzamboni · 🛗 zzamboni · 💆 zzamboni

I am a Senior Engineering Manager, IT Architect and Researcher with 29 years of experience building systems and leading teams in startups as well as big companies. I have experience working with and leading remote teams. I possess a strong combination of leadership, conceptual and technical skills with excellent communication abilities. I am a generalist but specialize in the areas of Computer Security, Cloud Computing and Configuration Management.

Key skills _____

Leadership Team and project management, systems and software architecture.

Computer Security Security architecture, risk management and compliance; secure software development;

virtualization and cloud computing security; intrusion detection and prevention; oper-

ating system and network security.

Communications and Research Excellent written and spoken communication skills, with more than 30 years of written

and spoken communication, research and teaching experience.

Systems and Development Unix/Linux systems engineering and administration, system health management and

monitoring, cloud platforms (Amazon, Cloud Foundry, VMware), software development

experience (Ruby, Python, C, Perl, LISP, etc.).

Configuration management CFEngine, Ansible, Puppet.

Languages Spanish (native), English (100%), German (60% - B1 level).

Experience _____

Swisscom 2014 – Present Switzerland/U.S.A.

ENTERPRISE ARCHITECT AND IT CLOUDS SOLUTION SECURITY ARCHITECT

Apr 2019 – Present

- As a Solution Security Architect for IT Clouds...
 - I define and manage the security features and characteristics of Swisscom's cloud offerings, as a member of the Swisscom IT Clouds leadership team.
 - I maintain cloud platform and service compliance with internal, contractual and regulatory standards (e.g. ISO27001, ISAE3402/3000, FINMA and GDPR).
 - I established Security Champions initiative to promote and improve a culture of security responsibility.
 - I established organization-wide processes for risk management, threat modeling, audits and penetration testing.
 - I am the point of contact for CISO-level interactions with Swisscom's cloud customers.
- · As an Enterprise Architect, I define future Swisscom products and solutions as part of the Swisscom Enterprise Architecture team.

ARCHITECT AND ENGINEERING LEADER FOR MONITORING, HEALTH AND STATE MANAGEMENT

Aug 2014 - Apr 2019

- Starting as a project lead and architect, I established and managed a team of up to 16 engineers that designed, implemented and operated monitoring and logging capabilities for Swisscom's IaaS and PaaS cloud offerings.
- Unified platform and service monitoring components into one cohesive pipeline, reducing costs and increasing efficiency by 20%.
- Defined architecture and oversaw implementation of customer-facing monitoring and logging services.
- Designed and implemented the initial version of the Orchard monitoring platform for Swisscom's Application Cloud.
- Defined and implemented integrations between Jira and OpsGenie for alerting of user-reported incidents.
- Managed business relationship and technical implementation of OpsGenie for alert management in IT Clouds.
- · Managed engineering relationship with VMware for integration of their products in Swisscom's monitoring systems.

CFEngine AS

2011 – 2014 Norway/U.S.A. (remote)

SENIOR SECURITY ADVISOR AND PRODUCT MANAGER

Oct 2011 – Jun 2014

- Participated in the development of the CFEngine language roadmap and security strategy.
- Overall CFEngine Advocate, with a special focus on security.
- Gave talks, wrote articles and blog posts, taught classes, and in general spread the word about CFEngine.
- Published and promoted book Learning CFEngine (O'Reilly Media).
- Established and led the CFEngine Design Center project through its initial implementation phase.

HP Enterprise Services 2009 – 2011 Mexico

ACCOUNT SECURITY OFFICER AND SERVICE DELIVERY CONSULTANT

Nov 2009 - Oct 2011

- First point of contact for security-related issues for HP enterprise customers in Mexico, some of them with international presence.
- Initiated, advised and managed security-related projects.
- · Handled communication and coordination between technical teams involved in security initiatives.
- Oversaw all security-related aspects of the design, implementation and delivery of IT Outsourcing projects.
- Performed analysis, design and implementation of solutions in multiple areas of expertise, including system automation, configuration management, system administration, system design, virtualization, performance and security.

IBM Zurich Research Lab 2001 – 2009 Switzerland

RESEARCH STAFF MEMBER Oct 2001 – Oct 2009

- · I worked in various research projects in intrusion detection, malware containment, and virtualization security, including:
 - Project Phantom: Security for VMware virtual environments using virtual machine introspection.
 - Billy Goat: An active worm-detection and capture system, deployed in the IBM internal and external networks.
 - Router-based Billy Goat: An active worm-capture device deployed at the network boundary and coupled with a border router to effectively and automatically spoof every unused IP address outside the local network.
 - Exorcist: Host-based, behavior-based intrusion detection using sequences of system calls.

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM)

1991 - 1996

Mexico

HEAD OF COMPUTER SECURITY AREA

Aug 1995 – Aug 1996

- Established UNAM's first Intrusion Response Team, which has since evolved into a much larger organization.
- Supervised up to nine people working on different projects related to computer security.
- · Supervised and participated in the direct monitoring of the security of a Cray supercomputer and 22 Unix workstations.
- Provided security services to the whole University, including incident response, security information, auditing and teaching.
- Established the celebration of the *International Computer Security Day* (sponsored by the Association for Computing Machinery) at UNAM. Acted as the main organizer of the event for two years (1994 and 1995). This event has grown and divided into the *Computer Security Day* (a one-day event) and the *Seguridad en Cómputo* (Computer Security) conference (a multi-day event).
- Designed and headed development of an audit-analysis tool for Unix systems (SAINT).

System Administrator Nov 1991 – Aug 1995

- Part of the system administration team at the University's Supercomputing Center, managing UNAM's Cray Y-MP Supercomputer and related systems.
- Responded to security incidents affecting the Cray supercomputer and related workstations.

Education _

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN, U.S.A. 1996–2001

 ${\it Using Internal Sensors for Computer Intrusion Detection}, {\it Advisor: Eugene H. Spafford.}$

Certifications

CERTIFIED INFORMATION SYSTEMS SECURITY PROFESSIONAL (CISSP)

April 2019

SAFe® 4 Certified Product Owner/Product Manager

July 2017

Published books_____

LITERATE CONFIGURATION

Self-published 2019

LEARNING HAMMERSPOON

Self-published 2018

LEARNING CFENGINE

O'Reilly Media 2012, Self-published 2017

Research, Publications, and References _____

Available upon request.

Full Curriculum Vitæ available at https://zzamboni.org/vita/.